Guide to The Reaper Records, 1979-1989
Department of Special Collections
The Reaper Records,
1979-1989
M0512
4.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Records pertain to the editorial process of THE REAPER, its production, finiancial management, and other miscellaneous business, as well as the literary interests and opinions of its editors and contributing authors. Included is correspondence between the poetry editors Mark Jarman and Robert McDowell; letters received from authors, subscribers, and others; submitted manuscripts; production files for most issues consisting of original contents, paste up, galleys, artwork, related correspondence, and printing flats; grant applications; mailing records; clippings and reviews; and other business records.
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1988.
Biography
The Reaper, a small poetry and fiction magazine founded by Robert McDowell and Mark Jarman, was an important voice in the movement in American poetry known as the New Narrative or the New Formalism, which began in the late seventies. The movement attacked the free verse poetics of autobiographical experiences that the Beats had espoused in the 1950's. The New Formalists argued for a return to meter and rhyme, recognition of the importance of narrative, and the inclusion of public as well as private experience. From Issue #1, published in 1980, to Issue #19/20, the final issue, to be published in 1990, The Reaper was strongly committed to narrative poetry and published many of the authors working in this new form including Dana Gioia, Rita Dove, Frederick Morgan, Liam Rector, Chris Semansky, Chase TWichell, and Rusty White. In addition, The Reaper published Jarman and McDowell's reviews and critidal essays on modern poetry that prompted reviewers to call it "feisty and iconoclastic."
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The records of The Reaper, dating from 1979 to 1989, are arranged in three series: correspondence, issue files, and business files. They document the editorial process of the journal, its production, financial management, and other miscellaneous business aspects, as well as the literary interests and opinions of its editors and contributing authors.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Carter, Jared.; Cervantes, James.; Dove, Rita.; Eberhart, Richard, 1904-.; Flynn, Richard.; Gioia, Dana.; Haas, Barbara.; Hall, Donald, 1928-.; Hilton, David, 1938-.; Jarman, Mark.; Joselow, Beth.; McDowell, Robert, 1953-.; Mastro, Mark Anthony.; Morgan, Frederick, 1922-.; Rector, Liam, 1949-.; Semansky, Chris.; Twichell, Chase, 1950-.; Wilhemous, Tom.; American literature--20th. century.; Poetry, modern--20th. century.
Collection Contents
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1980-1989
  Series I, Correspondence, is divided into two sections. The first contains correspondence of the editors, Mark Jaxman, Robert McDowell, and Tom Wilhemus. The bulk of this section is letters between Jarnian and McDowell, poetry editors, 1980-1989, discussing poems submitted, production details, financial matters, their joint articles, and general literary matters, with some personal news included. Manuscripts are included with some of the letters; in addition there are photocopies of a typescript poem and a letter from Robert Bly to Robert McDowell, 1985. There are also other letters of Robert McDowell and a small number of letters from Tom Wilhemus, fiction editor. Correspondence in this section is separated by editor and then arranged chronologically. The second section consists of letters to The Reaper from potential and published authors, subscribers, and readers, including a special file of correspondence with British poets. These letters are arranged alphabetically, with the general alphabet preceding files for specific authors. Some of the letters from authors include poetry manuscripts submitted for consideration. Authors represented by more than one or two letters were separated from the general alphabet and include Jared Carter, Rita Dove, Dana Gioia, Donald Ha, Liani Rector, and Chase Twichell. AU of the correspondence is open to researchers except for two letters by Donald Hall which were pulled from the collection due to their confidential nature.
  - Jarman, Mark to Robert McDowell, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jarman, Mark to Robert McDowell, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jarman, Mark to Robert McDowell, 1987-1989 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - McDowell, Robeit to Mark Jarman, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - MCDcwell, Robert to Mark Janiian, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - McDowell, Robext to Mark Jarman, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - McDowell, Robert to Mark Jarmnan, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - McDowell, Robert to Mark Jarman, 1988-1989 and undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dowel, Robert. Letters, 1985-1987 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wilheinus, Toni. Letters, 1985 and undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to The Reaper: A-B, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to The Reaper: C-D, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Carter, Jared, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Ceivantes, James, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Dove, Rita, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters to The Reaper: E-G, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Eberhait, Richard, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Flynn, Richard, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Gioia, Dana, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters to The Reaper: H, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Haas, Barbara, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Hall, Donald, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Hall, Donald, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Hilton, David, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters to The Reaper: I-K, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Joselow, Beth, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters to The Reaper: L, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Ma-Mh, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Mastro, Mark Anthony, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Mi-Mz, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Morgan, Frederick, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters to The Reaper: N-P, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Q-R, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Rector, Liam, 1983 and undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letters to The Reaper: S-T, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Semansky, chris, 1985 and undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters to The Reaper: Twichell, chase, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letters to The Reaper: U-Z, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letters to The Reaper: [No last name], 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence with British poets, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Graham Chainey, Tony Curtis, Douglas Dunn, D.J.Enright, Duncan Forbes, Mike Jenkins, Kevin Porter, Jon Silkin, David Sweetnian, and D.M.Thornas.
- Series 2: Issue files, 1979-1988
  Series II, Issue Files, documents the production of The Reaper, and is primarily arranged by issue number; photocopies of the table of contents from each issue are included with this guide. Each issue may or may not include the following files: original contents, photocopies of contents, paste up, photocopy of paste up, galleys, artwork, related correspondence from authors, artists, and between the editors, and miscellaneous items such as backgrOund materials, revisions of lead essays, and extra covers. Oversized and non-paper items such as paste up sheets, printing flats, and printing plates have been boxed separately. Issues 1 through 11 are especially well documented; there are partial files on Issues 12, 13, 16, and 18. Issues 14, 15, and 17 are not represented in the collection at all. The remainder of this series consists of accepted poems that were never published and other miscellaneous manuscripts.
  - Issue #1: Original contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Issue #1: Paste up (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Issue #1: Photocopy of paste up (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Issue #1: Essays from "After the Flood" Workshop,1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Issue #2: Original contents (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Issue #2: Photocopy of contents (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Issue #2: Typeset galleys (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Issue #2: Photocopy of paste up (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Issue #2: Miscellaneous items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Issue #3: Original contents (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Issue #3: Photocopy of contents (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Issue #3: Paste up (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Issue #3: Photocopy of paste up (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Issue #4: Original contents (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Issue #4: Photocopy of contents (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Issue #4 :Artwork (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Issue #4: Related correspondence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Issue #5: Original contents (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Issue #5: Photocopy of contents (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Issue #5 :Related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Issue #5: Extra covers (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Issue #6: Original contents (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Issue #6: Photocopy of contents (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Issue #6: Related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Issue #7: Original contents (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Issue #7 :Photocopy of contents (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Issue #7: Photocopy of galleys (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Issue #7: Related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Issue #8: Original contents (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Issue #8: Photocopy of contents (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Issue #8: Related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Issue #8: Revisions of lead essay (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Issue #9: Original contents (partial) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Issue #9: Photocopy of contents (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Issue #9: Related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Issue #9: "The Dogtown Letters" version 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Issue #9: "The Dogtown Letters" version 2 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Issue #10: Original contents (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Issue #10: Photocopy of contents (partial) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Issue #10: Paste up (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Issue #10: Related correspondence (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Issue #11: Original contents (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Issue #11:Paste up (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Issue #11:Related correspondence (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Issue #11: "How to Write Narrative Poetry: A Reaper checklist" - earlier version of lead essay (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Issue #12: Original contents (partial) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Issue #13: "Forever Young: A Survey, Conducted, by The Reaper" - typescript, letter, notes (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Issue #13: "Narrative and Awareness" by Barbara Haas (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Issue #16: Original contents (partial) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Issue #16:Related correspondence (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Issue #18: Original contents (partial) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Issue #18: Thotocopy of contents (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Issue #18: Related correspondence (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Accepted poems, unpublished (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Issue #2: Paste up (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Issue #5: Paste up (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Issue #6: Paste up (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Issue #7: Paste up (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Issue #8: Paste up (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous paste up sheets (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Issue #1: Printing flats (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Issue #2: Printing flats (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Issue #6: Printing flats (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Issue #7: Printing flats (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous printing flats (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Issue #1: Printing plates (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Business files, 1980-1988
  Series III, Business Files, concerns the non-literary side of The Reaper, primarily its financial affairs. Included are grant applications to the Coordinating Council of Literary Magazines, the Indiana Arts Commission, and the National Endowment for the Arts; notes and records of printing and publication costs; and purchase orders from libraries and bookstores. Non-financial materials in this series include mailing records, clippings and reviews, and a resume of Robert McDowell.
  - Bulk rate mailing records and address lists, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coordinating Council of Literary Magazines, grant applications, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising letter, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Indiana Arts Conmiission, grant applications, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Indiana State University Evansville, memoranda, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous business records (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, grant applications, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Printing and publication costs, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Resume, Robert McDowell, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Retail and library orders, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reviews of The Reaper, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)